<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><models><model><id><![CDATA[4]]></id><question><![CDATA[Andreas is a biophysicist. He has no interest nor any connection with Pharmacore Co. Andreas uses DNA polymerase regularly and is always shopping around for the best deal. Recently, the price of DNA polymerase has increased from $10 to $100 per unit over the past month due to short supply. Andreas observes from Pharmacore Co.’s website that they have an inventory of 20 tons of DNA polymerase (their main commercial good) still listed at $10. Andreas suspects the listed price of DNA polymerase will increase. Pharmacore Co.’s stock has stayed at a steady $20 per share for the past year. Andreas suspects that with the recent trend in DNA polymerase pricing Pharmacore Co.’s stock is worth much more than $20 per share. Knowing the above stated facts, Andreas offers Mike $21 dollars per share for a million shares. Mike sells the stock to Andreas. The following month the stock is up to $200 per share. 

If Mike asserts a claim based on misrepresentation against Andreas, will Mike prevail? 
]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(a). (a) adds the element of misrepresentation. The basic elements for misrepresentation are: 
(1) Defendant’s misrepresentation of a material fact, (2)  Defendant’s knowledge of falsity or reckless disregard for falsity, (3) Defendant’s intent to induce Plaintiff’s reliance, (4) Plaintiff’s actual, justifiable reliance, (5) Damages. 

Here, (a) provides the necessary element (1). The fourth element can be tricky in some fact patterns. Here, Andreas understands the technical details and we assume that Mike does not have as much technical understanding so Mike justifiably relies on Andreas’ misrepresentation. (b) is irrelevant. (c) and (d) are lacking the first element to misrepresentation. 
]]></explanation></model><model><id><![CDATA[5]]></id><question><![CDATA[The owner of a small airplane flies from New York to Los Angeles with one passenger. During the course of the flight a wing tears off due to the manufacturer not reinforcing the wing with materials that meet specification. Both the owner and the passenger use parachutes to float to the ground. The passenger breaks a knee on impact with the ground. 

If the passenger brings a negligence lawsuit against the owner for personal injuries is the passenger likely to prevail?
]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(a). Negligence elements include duty, breach, causation, and damages. Answer (a) is correct because the owner of the aircraft did not breach a duty to the passenger. Answer (b) is incorrect because causation is not at issue. Answer (c) is incorrect because the call of the question asks about negligence which does not use strict liability. Answer (d) is unrelated to the facts.]]></explanation></model><model><id><![CDATA[6]]></id><question><![CDATA[A restaurant patron enters a fine dining establishment and is seated near the wall On the wall a shelf is mounted which holds several flour barrels. Patron then orders fish sticks. While in the process of chewing a barrel of flour falls from the ceiling, lands on Patron’s arm, and breaks it. The shelf is in its original state.

Patron hires an attorney who brings a personal injury lawsuit against the fine dining restaurant. At trial, the attorney offers no testimony. On the restaurant’s motion to dismiss, the court should 
]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(c). The doctrine of res ipsa loquitor (“the thing speaks for itself”) applies. There are 4 requirements: (1) there must be no direct evidence connecting defendant’s behavior to the event, (2) the event must be of a kind that ordinarily would not happen “but for” someone’s negligence, (3) the instrumentality, at the time of the injury, must have been in the exclusive control of defendant, and (4) the injury must not have been due to plaintiff’s own actions. (a) is incorrect because even though the burden of proof is on the side of the plaintiff, the purpose of res ipsa loquitor is to prevents the necessity of direct evidence production. (b) because we are told that the shelf is in its original state. (d) is incorrect because the burden of proof is not on the defendant. ]]></explanation></model><model><id><![CDATA[7]]></id><question><![CDATA[“Mike’s Knives and Cutlery” shop was burglarized by an escaped innate from the mental institution down the street. The shop had an outer door made of solid steel with three deadbolt locks that were all engaged. The innate managed to pick the locks and easily remove a katana sword from one of the cabinets which Mike had negligently forgotten to lock the night before. The innate used the sword to kill a dozen random people. Bill managed to stop inmate from further killing, but only after sustaining several injuries which resulted in the disfigurement of his face. 

If Bill sues Mike for the injury he suffered, will Bill prevail? 
]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(d). The basic elements of negligence include duty, breach, causation, and damages. Here, Mike has a duty to act as a reasonable knife and cutlery shop owner would and to prevent foreseeable thefts of his knives and cutlery. Mike was reasonable in carrying out his duty because of the strong measures he took to prevent thieves from entering the store. However, if Mike knew there were lots of thieves in the neighborhood capable for picking deadbolt locks, his duty would require him to take further measures to prevent theft of dangerous objects. (a) is incorrect because Bill would have to show that Mike did not exercise reasonable care. Mike used a steel door with three deadbolt locks which is reasonable. (b) is incorrect because Mike did not breach his duty to act as a reasonable knife and cutlery shop owner would. (c) is incorrect because abnormally dangerous activities are not relevant to this question. ]]></explanation></model><model><id><![CDATA[8]]></id><question><![CDATA[A vacuum cleaner salesman walked up to a house with a white picket fence. The pathway leading to the door of the house was blocked by a gate. On the gate a sign read “Trespassers will be blown up with landmines.” The vacuum cleaner salesman disregarded the sign and entered anyway. Halfway to the door a mine exploded, removing the salesman’s right leg. 

Can the vacuum cleaner saleman recover damages from the inhabitant of the house? 
]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(c). Answer (c) is the best answer because people inhabiting houses may not use deadly force to protect property. Defense of property is an intentional tort where only reasonable force may be used to prevent trespass. Force that is likely to cause substantial harm or death is not reasonable in this particular situation. Furthermore, mechanical devices are treated as if a person has direct control. When a person has direct control of the instrumentality they can use judgment to determine reasonable force. Here, the vacuum cleaner salesman, at most, posed a minor irritation so the force used was unreasonable. (a) is incorrect because even though deadly force may be used to protect people it may not be against a salesman who poses no danger. (b) is incorrect because deadly force may not be used against trespassers even after a warning is given. (d) is incorrect because intent regarding the level of forced used does not matter. The fact that the salesman lost a leg indicates that deadly force was used. ]]></explanation></model><model><id><![CDATA[9]]></id><question><![CDATA[Tim noticed that a neighbor’s garage door was open so he decided to siphon gasoline out of the car stored inside without the neighbor’s knowledge. During the siphoning the gasoline ignited and Tim clothing caught on fire. John noticed Tim and the car on fire and acted quickly to put out the flames. In doing so, John saved Tim’s life and the neighbor’s car. 

Is John files a lawsuit against the neighbor to recover for personal injuries sustained during the rescue, will John prevail? ]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(d). The issue in this fact pattern is whether the neighbor was negligent. Here, the neighbor did not breach any duty because there was no duty owed. The fact that the garage door was left open would not be a breach of duty without more facts to indicate that residents have a duty to close their garage doors. Therefore, (d) is the best answer choice. (a) is incorrect because the result of his action is not relevant to whether he will prevail. The neighbor must have owed a duty to John. (b) is incorrect because it is entirely unrelated to the call of the question. (c) Assumption of risk is a defense in torts which bars a plaintiff from recovery against a negligent tortfeasor is the plaintiff voluntarily and knowing assumed the risks of a dangerous activity. Here, the tortfeasor was Tim; not the neighbor.  ]]></explanation></model><model><id><![CDATA[10]]></id><question><![CDATA[NewChem, Inc. used a chemical called InsulationX from 1990 until 2000. Harry, an employee of NewChem, Inc. installed InsulationX during that 10 year period until it was discovered in 2001 that InsulationX caused a disease called Xdeath. Due to 10 years of working closely with InsulationX, Harry had serious exposure to InsulationX’s pathogenic properties. Harry contracted Xdeath in 2001 and brought an action against NewChem, Inc. for strict liability in tort for failure to warn. The case is about to be tried before a jury. 

In this action, which of the following should the court decide as a matter of law? 
]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(b). Answer (b) is correct because it is the court’s job to set the standard of care. Here, the case can only go forward if the court determines that NewChem, Inc. will be held to the standard of a prudent manufacturer. Choices (a), (c), and (d) are incorrect because they all involve questions of fact which are to be determined by the jury. ]]></explanation></model><model><id><![CDATA[11]]></id><question><![CDATA[A motorist was driving at exactly the posted speed limit and observed a stop sign in the distance. As the motorist approached she applied pressure to the brake pedal and slowed her car. At the same time a pedestrian entered the crosswalk the motorist suffered a stroke and was rendered unconscious. Unfortunately, due to her unconscious state, the motorist stopped applying pressure to the brake pedal and drove through the stop sign, hitting the pedestrian. 

The pedestrian decided to sue motorist to recover for his injuries. At trial the parties stipulated that the motorist was driving as a reasonably prudent driver would up until being rendered unconscious. The parties also stipulated that the motorist had no prior history of strokes. 

Both parties made motions for directed verdicts. Whose motion should the court grant? ]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(c). The possible theories could either be intentional tort or negligence. Here, the motorist did not possess the requisite intent for intentional tort liability. There is also no direct evidence to suggest that the motorist failed to exercise reasonable care under the circumstances. Therefore, the court would have to find, as a matter of law that a jury could not find the motorist guilty of an intentional tort or negligence. Also, a statute that could make the motorist guilty of negligence per se would not apply because an unconscious act cannot be the basis for this kind of tort. (a) is incorrect because the motorist was not negligent. (b) is incorrect because, as discussed, negligence per se would not apply in this case. (d) is incorrect because the court would have to find in favor of the motorist because triable facts are not available to meet the elements of intentional tort or negligence theories. ]]></explanation></model><model><id><![CDATA[12]]></id><question><![CDATA[Federal law started requiring car companies to install seat belts in allow cars sold in the United States. CarCo used screws from ScrewCo to install their seat belts. Driver and Passenger were driving down a highway when Driver fell asleep at the wheel. The car, manufactured by CarCo, hit a tree on the side of the road which flung Passenger head-first into the tree causing a severe neck injury. Driver was killed after cracking his skull open against the steering wheel. Testing showed that one of the screws securing Passenger’s seat belt was defective and was the cause of Passenger’s ejection from the car. 

What is CarCo’s best defense against a negligence lawsuit brought by Passenger? 
]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(b). The elements of negligence are duty, breach, causation, and damages. If a defendant can show that they exercised reasonable care under the circumstances then they did not breach their duty and, therefore, the elements of negligence have not been met. It should be noted that strict liability usually applies in cases like these. (a) is incorrect because showing that Driver was negligent in causing the accident does not relieve CarCo of potential negligence in installing a defective screw. If CarCo could show that Driver’s negligence was independent or superseding they would have a better argument. (c) is incorrect because Passenger did not assume the risk of defective screws. (d) is incorrect because a manufacturer has a duty to inspect each element that goes into a finished product. ]]></explanation></model><model><id><![CDATA[13]]></id><question><![CDATA[Nick and Josh took a flight from Arizona to Washington on business. During the flight Josh confessed to Nick that he (Josh) had slept with Nick’s wife on several occasions and that from time to time other men “joined in the fun.” Nick decided not to make a scene because he did not want the Federal Marshals arresting him so he waited until Josh went to the bathroom to make his move. When Josh was entering Nick slammed the bathroom door intending for the door to strike Josh in the head. The door struck Josh’s head and closed which caused the lock to jam. Josh was unable to leave the bathroom until after the plane landed and an engineering crew released the jammed lock.

If Josh sues Nick for false imprisonment, will Josh prevail? 
]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(b). The tort of false imprisonment is an intentional tort and, therefore, has an intent requirement. Here, Nick intentionally slammed the bathroom door in order to strike Josh. This was a battery. The transferred intent doctrine applies to assault, battery, false imprisonment, and trespass to land. In this case, the intent to batter would transfer to false imprisonment. (a) is incorrect because false imprisonment is an intentional tort and not negligence. (c) would be the correct answer if Nick did not have the intent to batter which could then be transferred. (d) is incorrect because the call of the question does not relate to intentional infliction of emotional distress. ]]></explanation></model><model><id><![CDATA[14]]></id><question><![CDATA[A television anchor reported that a fireman lets the houses of people he dislikes burn to the ground if he’s on call. The television anchor went on to say that the fireman has lost his position due to his criminal acts when the fireman had actually received an offer for more money in another district. 

If the fireman files a lawsuit against the television anchor based on defamation, what proven facts would allow the television anchor to prevail?  ]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(a). When defamation is being asserted against a public figure there must be knowledge of falsity or reckless disregard for the truth. However, when a private individual is trying to prove defamation they must only show that the defamer acted unreasonably. Here, (a) corresponds to the “reasonable” standard which is enough for public figures or private individuals. (b) is incorrect because it doesn’t matter what the anchor believed. (c) is incorrect because even if the statement is retracted the damage has been done. (d) is incorrect because malice relates to the issue of damages and not the issue of liability. ]]></explanation></model><model><id><![CDATA[15]]></id><question><![CDATA[A family, consisting of two parents and a baby, bought a new ventilation system for their house. The system was designed by VentiCo which included a cooling component for CoolCo and a heating component from HotCo. The system was designed by VentiCo so that a user could set the temperate on the thermostat, located in the basement, to a specified temperature and the heating or cooling component would be activated as needed to adjust the temperature. VentiCo designed the system so that the cooling component released air into the basement and the heating component released air into the upstairs part of the house. After a successful installation, the parents set the thermostat to 70 degrees Fahrenheit. The basement was at 60 degrees Fahrenheit so the heating component began to blow hot air into the upstairs portion of the house where the baby was located. The temperature reached 165 degrees Fahrenheit and, as a result, the baby received brain damage due to long term heat exposure. ]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(a). There are several requirements for strict product liability which include the following: 

1) A defective product
2) There have been not significant alterations since reaching the user 
3) The seller must be in a business of selling the product
4) There must be damages which were caused by the defect
5) There is no privity requirement

According to the Restatement of Torts a design defect occurs “when the foreseeable risks of harm posed by the product could have been reduced or avoided by the adoption of a reasonable alternative design by the seller or other distributor, or a predecessor in the commercial chain of distribution, and the omission of the alternative design renders the product not reasonably safe.” Here, VentiCo will be strictly liable because it satisfies all the elements. (b)-(d) are incorrect because alternative designs made by HotCo and CoolCo would not have had any effect on the outcome. The defect was VentiCo’s so it would not be foreseeable for the “predecessors” mentioned in the Restatement to have been able to act. 
]]></explanation></model><model><id><![CDATA[16]]></id><question><![CDATA[Police officer observed Mike and Andreas smoking cigars in a public park where smoking was not allowed. A police officer observed Mike and Andreas and came over to give them a stern talking to. When the police officer arrived, he said he “I don’t like the way you’re looking at me!” to Andreas and then proceeded to beat Mike with his baton until Mike’s corpse was nothing but a pool of blood with a tissue mass in the center. Unknown to the police officer, Mike’s son had been watching behind a nearby tree and suffered from severe emotional distress. 

In an action for intentional infliction of emotional distress, who is likely to prevail? ]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(a). The elements for intentional infliction of emotional distress where someone else is intentionally physically harmed and a third party is suing are as follows: 

1) The third party is present for the physical injury.
2) They are closely related to the injured person.
3) The potential tortfeasor knows of the third party’s presence, and must be able to reasonably anticipate the third party’s distress resulting from the physical harm. 

Mike’s son meets elements 1 and 2, but not 3. He was present for the physical injury, is a closely related to the injured person, but the potential tortfeasor did not know of his presence. Andreas meets elements 1 and 3, but not 2. He was present for the physical injury and the potential tortfeasor knew of his presence, but he is not closely related to the injured person. ]]></explanation></model><model><id><![CDATA[17]]></id><question><![CDATA[GasCo is the only distributor of natural gas to houses in Gasville. GasCo mines the gas, purifies it, and distributes the gas using lines that they created and maintain. GasCo is known for having a high safety record and complying with all relevant regulations. Recently, GasCo has been plugging leaks caused by a group of teenagers who have been digging up the gas lines and poking holes in them. After the teenagers dug up a gas line and caused a leak, Bruno was severely injured while walking by and trying to light a cigarette. 

If Bruno brings a claim against GasCo, is he likely to prevail? ]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(a). This tort would have to be for negligence because there was no intent on the part of GasCo. The elements of negligence are duty, breach, causation, and damages. Here, the main issue is how far GasCo’s duty runs. (a) is correct because if GasCo was aware of the leaks being caused by teenagers a safety hazard would be foreseeable and GasCo would have a duty to take reasonable preventative measures. (b) is incorrect because strict product liability will not apply when there is no manufacturing or design defect involved. (c) is incorrect because using reasonable care to prevent human interference goes beyond the required duty of GasCo. (d) is incorrect because the teenagers’ intent is not relevant to GasCo’s duty. ]]></explanation></model><model><id><![CDATA[18]]></id><question><![CDATA[DamCo designed and built a dam in order to create a reservoir. A spillway specialist was hired to design and build the spillway portion of the dam which would allow for adjustment of water release. As required by the state, the spillway specialist filled for a permit to build the spillway. The permit application included a blueprint of the entire facility and the spillway specialist signed as a professional spillway specialist. After the dam was complete, a crack released water that damaged Plaintiff’s property. It has been established that the crack was caused by a design defect in the dam that was unrelated to the spillway. 

If Plaintiff sues spillway specialist on the theory of negligence will she prevail? ]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(b). (b) is correct because the crack was caused by a design defect that was unrelated to the spillway. The elements of negligence are duty, breach, causation, and damages. This question goes to whether there was a duty in the first place. The spillway specialist only worked with the spillway so her duty to use reasonable care in design and construction only extend to that portion of the overall structure. She would not have even had the opportunity to use reasonable care regarding the design which caused the crack. (a) is incorrect because it is not relevant. Whether a person is an agent or not would affect a company’s liability. Here, Plaintiff is suing the spillway specialist directly. (c) is incorrect because including a blueprint of something does create a duty that can later create liability. (d) is incorrect because joint and several liability requires that acts combine to proximately cause a plaintiff’s injuries. Here, the spillway specialist’s design was unrelated to the design of the rest of the dam so there is no proximate cause. ]]></explanation></model><model><id><![CDATA[19]]></id><question><![CDATA[Yeager bought a model airplane from Douglas, who deals in model airplane sales regularly. Douglas, knowingly, made the following false statements to Yeager just prior to the purchase.  

1) This model airplane can burn any kind of fuel. 

2) This model airplane will blow other airplanes out of the sky. 

3) This model airplane has a top speed of 150 miles per hour. 

If Yeager brings a claim against Douglas based on deception, which of the statements made by Douglas can Yeager use to support his claim? ]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(c). UCC §2-313 governs the creation of warranties. Any affirmation of facts promised by the seller become part of the bargain and creates an express warranty. However, the seller’s opinion or purported value of the item does not become part of the express warranty. This is also known as “puffery.” In 1) the seller claims that any kind of fuel can be burnt to propel the model plane. This is a material fact and not just opinion. Statement 2) is vague and clearly just opinion so it will be considered mere puffery. Statement 3) provides a value for the top speed which is something that can be measured and would not be considered just opinion information. Therefore, statements 1) and 3) can be used in Yeager’s claim which is answer (c). Note: Examining each of the elements of fraud in the context of this question can be beneficial to better understand fraud analysis. ]]></explanation></model><model><id><![CDATA[20]]></id><question><![CDATA[Andreas bought a toy magnifying glass for his six year old son David. The intended use was to roast small creatures by focusing sunlight through the magnifying lens. One day, David was roasting ants on the sidewalk when his friend Anthony came by and wanted to play. Anthony began roasting ants when the magnifying glass suddenly exploded, thereby, causing injury to Anthony’s hand. 

Who can Anthony recover from? ]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(b). Products liability is the proper theory to sue under because the magnifying glass was being used for its intended use and the user who was injured was a foreseeable user. It does not matter that Andreas, an adult, bought the magnifying glass. It only matters that it was intended to be used by his child and it is foreseeable that David would invite other friends to also play. (a) is incorrect because there is nothing to suggest Andreas is negligent. The negligence analysis is duty, breach, causation, and damages. Letting kids burn ants may or may not be a breach of duty as a reasonable parent, but even if this was a breach it did not cause the harm. (c) is incorrect because the privity requirement for warranties generally no longer applies. (d) is incorrect because, as explained, Andreas will not be held liable for negligence and the manufacturer will be held liable under products liability theory. ]]></explanation></model><model><id><![CDATA[21]]></id><question><![CDATA[While driving his car down a country road with very little traffic, Tommy was distracted by the scenery outside his driver side window. As a result, Tommy went through a stop light without braking. At the same time, James approached the intersection cross directionally and also failed to stop at his stop sign after looking in both directions and not seeing anyone stopped at the intersection. The two cars collided. Tommy was injured and James was not. Assume that the jurisdiction where this intersection is located adheres to the doctrine of contributory negligence. 

If Tommy sues James for his injuries, who will prevail? ]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(b). In states that recognize contributory negligence it will act as a complete defense. In comparative negligence states the court will assess each party’s responsibility for the accident. (a) is incorrect because looking both ways and failing to stop at a stop sign is clearly negligent. Negligence analysis involves duty, breach, causation, and damages. Both parties had a duty to stop at the stop sign and breached that duty which caused Tommy’s injuries. (c) is incorrect because it is immaterial with regard to Tommy’s recovery. (d) is incorrect because nothing in the facts indicates that James had a last clear chance opportunity to avoid the collision. ]]></explanation></model><model><id><![CDATA[22]]></id><question><![CDATA[The host of a major news network was asked to deliver a speech to a group of wealthy people belonging to a charity group. After talking for a few minutes someone in the audience raised their hand and asked what the host thought of firefighters. The host then went on a diatribe about how firefighters were overpaid and overrated and should not be allowed to unionize because apes could do their jobs. While this was happening Ben, the only firefighter in the audience, started to get glares from around the room.

If Ben sues the host for defamation, who will prevail?]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(d). Statements that defame have a tendency to harm the plaintiff. It is extremely difficult to prove that statements made about an entire class are a reflection on a single individual. For this same reason (a) in correct. (b) is incorrect because there is nothing to link the host’s statements with Ben. If there were facts to indicate that the host was actually talking about Ben and the audience was aware of this then there would be a good argument for (b) as the correct answer. (c) is incorrect because Ben would not have to show monetary damages to win a defamation suit.]]></explanation></model><model><id><![CDATA[23]]></id><question><![CDATA[Amanda lives near a field with high brush where she walks her dog daily. In fact, many other dog owners walk their dogs in the same field. One afternoon, Amanda took her dog for a walk through the field using a dog leash. Ranger Dan was hiding in a bush in the field with an assault rifle and let out a loud burst of rifle shots. The burst startled the dog and the dog then broke its leash. The dog ran until it encountered Jim. The dog then bit off Jim’s ear off because of the anxiety the loud burst caused. 

If Jim sues Amanda, who will prevail? ]]></question><explanation><![CDATA[(b). Simply owning a dog does not make the owner strictly liable for their dog’s actions unless the dog has displayed dangerous tendencies in the past. The fact pattern does not indicate that the dog has previous injured anyone so (b) is the correct answer. (a) is incorrect because, as explained, dog owners are not usually strict liable for their pets. (c) is incorrect because it would also hold owners strictly liable for the actions of their dogs. (d) is incorrect because Amanda acted as a reasonable dog owner would because she used a leash. Even if she was in breach of her duty as a reasonable dog owner her actions are not the proximate cause of Jim’s injuries because rifle fire was not foreseeable in a field where people walk their dogs. ]]></explanation></model></models>